timothy martin

70 E. 10th Street, #9R • New York, NY 10003 (917) 826-6146 • timothymartin76@gmail.com

PROFILE

Senior data analytics professional with more than a decade of experience in business intelligence, scientific research, and performance management. Director of technical teams and information management projects with a focus on designing curated data experiences for end users. Expert in identifying and interpreting trends in large and varied datasets, and producing informative metrics and interactive visualizations which drive business decisions. Extensive experience using BI and statistical tools. Skilled at developing front-end applications and dashboards for evaluation of disparate data sources.

EXPERIENCE

CHIEF ANALYTICS OFFICER, NYC Buildings

New York, NY 2016 – Present

Provide strategic technical leadership in the development of analytic metrics and information management services that move data-driven capabilities into the hands of business users. Responsible for directing the Analytics and Data Science Division including research and reporting initiatives, performance measurement, GIS, and predictive modeling.

BUSINESS INTELLIGENCE MANAGER, NYC 311

New York, NY 2014 – 2016

Managed activities of technical teams responsible for development of BI reports, KPIs, dashboards, and data models. Performed data mining, statistical analysis, and predictive modeling of complaint data, customer behavior, and demographics. Created interactive data visualizations and maps. Presented high-level metrics and analysis to senior staff.

WSI PROGRAM MANAGER, NYC DEP

New York, NY 2009 – 2014

Facilitated design and evaluation of a \$12 million early warning system for NYC, including development of a real-time, smart grid platform for remote monitoring. Developed and managed KPIs to evaluate WSI program operations, performance, and sustainability. Implemented large-scale, scientific data analytics applications. Presented findings to industry leaders.

RESEARCH SCIENTIST, NYC DEP

New York, NY 2005 – 2009

Developed and managed a pharmaceutical contaminant monitoring plan for NYC source water. Published research and analysis of findings. Performed analysis of environmental and public health data to support operational decision-making.

BUSINESS OPERATIONS ANALYST, L'OCCITANE

New York, NY 2003 – 2004

ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENTIST, SOTA ENVIRONMENTAL TECHNOLOGY

San Diego, CA 2001 – 2003

AGROFORESTRY VOLUNTEER, US PEACE CORPS

Malawi, Africa 1999 – 2001

TECHNICAL SKILLS

OBIEE
SQL
VBA
D3.js
R
Tableau
QGIS
CartoDB
Python
Access
ArcGIS
HTML5

EDUCATION

MPA, ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCE & POLICY Columbia University, New York, NY

2005

1998

BA, ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCE

Willamette University, Salem, OR